<clinical_study rank="48750">
  
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 05, 2016</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02130349</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IBDSL biobank project</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02130349</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>IBDSL Biobank Project. Molecular Markers for Diagnosis and Therapy Response in IBD.</brief_title>
  <acronym>IBDSL</acronym>
  <official_title>IBDSL Biobank Project. Molecular Markers for Diagnosis and Therapy Response in IBD. A Prospective Population Based Biobank of Inflammatory Bowel Disease Patients in Zuid Limburg, The Netherlands.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Maastricht University Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Maastricht University Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Netherlands: Medical Ethics Review Committee (METC)</authority>
    <authority>Netherlands: The Central Committee on Research Involving Human Subjects (CCMO)</authority>
    <authority>Netherlands: Ministry of Health, Welfare and Sport</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The IBD South Limburg (IBDSL) project was initially designed as a prospective population
      based cohort study. Since 1991, all new IBD cases have been enrolled in the cohort and
      prospectively followed. As from 2011, the cohort is being scaled up into a population based
      biobank and focus expanded from epidemiology towards exploring underlying biologic
      mechanisms and identifying markers to predict disease course or therapy response.

      Every adult IBD patient, diagnosed in and permanently residing in South Limburg (The
      Netherlands), is eligible to participate. The population based nature was reached via a
      multi-faceted approach; incident cases were prospectively identified through the
      participating hospitals, and missed patients were retrospectively identified using the
      nationwide histopathology registry. In 2011, over 3500 patients were included, which
      represents 93% of the IBD population in South Limburg.

      The cohort includes baseline data, such as IBD phenotype, extent, location, behaviour, extra
      intestinal manifestations, medication, surgery, comorbidity and demographics. Data has
      prospectively been updated through chart review (clinical data), questionnaires (i.e.
      quality of life) and linkage to the authority database (vital state, residence). The biobank
      includes serum, plasma, DNA, faeces, biopsies and exhaled air.

      We welcome new collaborations. Applications for collaboration are first to be approved by
      our IBD-SL committee.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background: Inflammatory Bowel Disease (IBD), encompassing Crohn's Disease (CD) and
      Ulcerative Colitis (UC), is a chronic disabling condition of the intestine. Most patients
      experience sequences of exacerbation in which quality of life is often impaired. Also
      society endures heavily, as IBD healthcare costs are estimated at 4.6-5.6 billion euros per
      year and high rates of unemployment and work disability are reported. The current incidence
      estimate is 256.000 Europeans per year, and yet increases.

      IBD arises from complex interactions between a genetically altered intestinal immune
      response, environmental factors and intestinal microbiota. Disease phenotypes are
      heterogeneous and predicting individual disease course or therapy response is still merely
      possible; treatment of choice for instance remains a trial-and-error based succession of
      regimens. Further exploration of the underlying biologic mechanisms, and the identification
      and validation of non-invasive markers to predict disease course and therapy response are
      the foremost challenges in IBD field at this moment.

      Deeply phenotyped IBD cohorts with a biobank are ideal tools for this type of research, and
      are warranted. Most IBD biobanks reflect hospital based populations thereby over
      representing severe and therapy refractory patients. However, many hypotheses require
      designs with a full IBD spectrum. Secondly, phenotypes are mostly ascertained
      retrospectively, which makes results prone for bias. As no prospective population based
      biobank excists, we started the population based IBD South Limburg (IBDSL) biobank project.

      IBDSL: The IBDSL project was first established in 1991, when gastroenterologists started
      prospectively registering all IBD patients residing in South Limburg, the Netherlands. As
      from 2011, this cohort is being scaled up into a biobank and focus expanded from
      epidemiology towards exploring underlying biologic mechanisms and identifying markers to
      predict disease course or therapy response.

      Population: Every adult IBD patient, diagnosed in South Limburg after 1991 and permanently
      residing in South Limburg (the Netherlands), is eligible to participate. The population
      based nature was reached via a multi-faceted approach; incident cases were prospectively
      identified through the participating hospitals, and missed patients were retrospectively
      identified using the nationwide histopathology registry. In 2011, over 3500 patients were
      included, representing &gt;93% of the IBD population in South Limburg. Adults and partners of
      included patients serve as controls.

      Datacollection: All eligible IBD patients will be contacted and asked to participate.
      Patients will be visited at home or in hospital by a research nurse. After informed consent,
      DNA, serum, plasma, exhaled air and stool are collected. All data will be added into a
      custommade web-based data management system (MACRO). All biomaterials are stored in the
      central biobank facility of the MUMC.

      Additional information: IBDSL is a Dutch consortium comprising the gastroenterology
      departments of Maastricht University Medical Centre+ and the general district hospitals
      Orbis MC Sittard-Geleen and Atrium MC Heerlen. IBDSL is investigator initiated and has been
      funded by the consortium members. IBDSL has been approved by the Ethics Committee of the
      Maastricht University Medical Centre (METC 10-2-071, NL31636.068.10), and meets the ethical
      standards of the declaration of Helsinki. We welcome new collaborations. Applications for
      collaboration are first to be approved by our IBD-SL committee.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Cohort, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <target_duration>25 Years</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Concentration of seral, fecal, or volatile (exhaled air) biomarkers that reflect disease course and therapy response.</measure>
    <time_frame>Disease course is monitored at baseline, and at every consequent hospital visit (at least annually) until lost-to-follow-up (death, migration out of region, withdraw). Biomaterial is collected at a (non-specified) timepoint after diagnosis.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Primary aim of IBDSL: identify/validate markers that predict disease course and therapy response.
Focus lies on all future potent biomarkers (not possible to specify at this timepoint) in blood, dna, faeces, exhaled air and biopsies. Identifying new biomarkers is done by a bolomic approach, in order to find a biomarker(-set) that predict specific aspects of disease course (severe or mild disease course, occurence of extra-intestinal manifestations and/or surgery) and therapy response (chance of therapy success). Validation of already identified biomarkers will be done in a hypothesis driven approach.
Disease course and therapy response are reflected by endoscopic activity, clinical activity scores, number of flares, hospitalisations, surgeries, extra intestinal manifestations, comorbidity. These parameters are monitored at baseline, and at every consequent hospital visit (at least annually) until lost-to-follow-up (death, migration out of region, withdraw).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Epidemiologic parameters</measure>
    <time_frame>Disease course is monitored at baseline, and at every consequent hospital visit (at least annually) until lost-to-follow-up (death, migration out of region, withdrawal). Epidemiologic parameters are determined annually (since 1991)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Secondary aim of IBDSL: Periodic analysis of epidemiologic parameters
Epidemiology is reflected by incidence, prevalence, mortality, standardized comorbidic incidence ratios, and (environmental) assocations/risk factors.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>3</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">5000</enrollment>
  <condition>IBD</condition>
  <condition>Crohns Disease</condition>
  <condition>Ulcerative Colitis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Crohns Disease</arm_group_label>
    <description>IBD patients diagnosed with Crohn's disease</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ulcerative colitis</arm_group_label>
    <description>IBD patients diagnosed with ulcerative colitis</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>IBD-Undefined</arm_group_label>
    <description>IBD patients with undefined IBD</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      DNA Serum Plasma Stool Exhaled air Biopsies
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        All adult IBD patients (&gt;18 years) residing permanently in South Limburg are eligible. IBD
        was diagnosed by certified gastroenterologists according to the Lennard-Jones criteria,
        and was proven by endoscopic and/or radiologic evidence and by histologic evidence.

        To capture the full South Limburg IBD population, a multifaceted approach was used.
        Incident cases were prospectively identified through the three hospitals. Missed patients
        were retrospectively identified using PALGA, the nationwide histopathology registry
        containing data on all endoscopic biopsies.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All adult IBD patients (&gt;18 years) residing permanently in South Limburg are
             eligible. IBD was diagnosed by certified gastroenterologists according to the
             Lennard-Jones criteria, and was proven by endoscopic and/or radiologic evidence and
             by histologic evidence.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  &lt;18 years,
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marieke Pierik, PhD, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>MUMC</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Marieke Pierik, PhD, MD</last_name>
    <email>m.pierik@mumc.nl</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Atrium Medical Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Heerlen</city>
        <state>Limburg</state>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Liekele Oostenbrug, PhD, MD</last_name>
      <email>l.oostenbrug@atriummc.nl</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Maastricht University medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Maastricht</city>
        <state>Limburg</state>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Marieke Pierik, PhD, MD</last_name>
      <email>m.pierik@mumc.nl</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Orbis Medical Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sittard</city>
        <state>Limburg</state>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Marielle Romberg-Camps, PhD, MD</last_name>
      <email>m.camps@orbisconcern.nl</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.ibdzl.nl</url>
    <description>Information for patients (in Dutch)</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>March 2016</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 15, 2016</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 24, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>IBD</keyword>
  <keyword>Crohns Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Ulcerative Colitis</keyword>
  <keyword>Cohort</keyword>
  <keyword>Biobank</keyword>
  <keyword>Population based</keyword>
  <keyword>IBDSL</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    
    <mesh_term>Colitis, Ulcerative</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Crohn Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  
</clinical_study>