<clinical_study rank="210794">
  
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 05, 2016</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00004983</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>BROWNS (completed)</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01DK048160</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00004983</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Education and Group Support for Diabetic Hispanics</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases (NIDDK)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases (NIDDK)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this ongoing work in Starr County, located on the Texas-Mexico border, is to
      conduct clinical studies to determine the effectiveness of diabetes self-management programs
      designed specifically for Mexican Americans. The programs meet national standards for
      diabetes self-management education. They are provided in community settings with the primary
      purpose of improving the health of Mexican Americans with diabetes and their family members,
      who either have diabetes or are at risk for developing diabetes.

      The diabetes self-management programs are provided in Spanish and are directed by bilingual
      Hispanic clinical nurse specialists, dietitians, and community health workers. Key elements
      of the programs include instruction on nutrition, self-monitoring of blood glucose,
      exercise, and other diabetes self-management topics, as well as group support to promote
      behavioral changes.

      In the original study (1994-1998), 256 Mexican American adults diagnosed with type 2
      diabetes and 256 family members or other support persons were enrolled. For one year, the
      people with diabetes, along with their family members, attended small group sessions held in
      churches, community health clinics, adult day care centers, and schools. Information on the
      effectiveness of the program was collected at 3, 6, and 12 months; and annually thereafter.

      Findings of the original study suggested that the program had a positive impact on diabetes
      metabolic control. Levels of diabetes knowledge and rates of glucose self-monitoring and
      attendance suggested that a shorter program - one that incorporated critical elements of the
      previous successful strategy - might result in similar improvements. Thus, the goal of the
      new study, funded in June 1999, was to shorten the original program and to compare it to the
      previous successful program in terms of short- and long-term health outcomes.

      To identify key components of the previous program, we are exploring differences between
      subjects who successfully integrated self-care components of the program and who experienced
      significant improvements in metabolic control and those who were not as successful. The
      program is being revised and shortened, based on this information. Beginning in April 2000,
      we will start recruiting participants for the clinical trial of the revised program.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 1999</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2006</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2006</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <condition>Diabetes Mellitus, Non-Insulin-Dependent</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>diabetes self-management education</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosed with type 2 diabetes ([a] two verifiable FBS test results of 140 mg/dl or
             above or [b] taking or have taken insulin or hypoglycemic agents for at least one
             year in the past)

          -  Willing to participate

          -  A family member, preferably a spouse or first-degree relative, who agrees to
             participate

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Migrant farm workers (not available for the year-long program)

          -  Pregnant

          -  Medical conditions for which changes in diet and exercise levels would be
             contraindicated
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>35 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sharon A. Brown</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>The University of Texas at Austin</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The University of Texas at Austin</name>
      <address>
        <city>Austin</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>78701</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brown SA, Hanis CL. A community-based, culturally sensitive education and group-support intervention for Mexican Americans with NIDDM: a pilot study of efficacy. Diabetes Educ. 1995 May-Jun;21(3):203-10.</citation>
    <PMID>7758387</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brown SA. Meta-analysis of diabetes patient education research: variations in intervention effects across studies. Res Nurs Health. 1992 Dec;15(6):409-19.</citation>
    <PMID>1448572</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brown SA, Hanis CL. Culturally competent diabetes education for Mexican Americans: the Starr County Study. Diabetes Educ. 1999 Mar-Apr;25(2):226-36.</citation>
    <PMID>10531848</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brown SA, Upchurch SL, Garcia AA, Barton SA, Hanis CL. Symptom-related self-care of Mexican Americans with type 2 diabetes: preliminary findings of the Starr County Diabetes Education Study. Diabetes Educ. 1998 May-Jun;24(3):331-9.</citation>
    <PMID>9677951</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2010</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 12, 2010</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 13, 2000</firstreceived_date>
  <keyword>diabetes mellitus, type 2</keyword>
  <keyword>diabetes self-management education</keyword>
  <keyword>diabetes self-care</keyword>
  <keyword>blood glucose self-monitoring</keyword>
  <keyword>health education</keyword>
  <keyword>patient education</keyword>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  
</clinical_study>