<clinical_study rank="186042">
  
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 05, 2016</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00324493</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MUSFIH2004</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00324493</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Musculoskeletal Function in Hemophilia</brief_title>
  <official_title>Musculoskeletal Function in Hemophilia in Developing Countries</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Christian Medical College, Vellore, India</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Christian Medical College, Vellore, India</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>India: Institutional Review Board</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Hemophilia, which results from deficiency of factor VIII or IX, is a common hereditary
      X-linked bleeding disorder affecting up to 10/100,000 population. About 60-70% of them have
      severe disease (factor level &lt;1%). This group is characterized by the occurrence of frequent
      spontaneous bleeding into joints and soft tissues. If inadequately treated, it results in
      progressive damage to joints and muscles leading to crippling deformities. Close clinical
      observation of these patients over many years has shown that those with &gt;1% levels have much
      less bleeding compared to those with less than 1%. This observation has gained immense
      clinical importance in planning therapy for these patients.

      To prevent progressive joint damage, the missing factor needs to be replaced. Much has
      evolved in this practice in the last 50 years. From administration of whole blood in the
      beginning, to plasma and cryoprecipitate, to purified plasma-derived concentrates and
      finally recombinant factor concentrates. The standard of therapy now is to replace factors
      frequently enough to maintain &gt;1% factor levels at all times (&#8220;prophylaxis&#8221;) or administer
      immediately on premonition or earliest signs of bleeding (&#8220;on demand&#8221; therapy). This has
      greatly enhanced the quality of life of people with hemophilia. However, the optimal
      regimens of factor replacement remain to be defined. The definition of what is optimal
      management of this chronic condition, currently incurable for the vast majority of patients,
      varies significantly in different parts of the world, depending on practicality and social
      expectations. Models have care have been developed in Western countries based on careful
      documentation of outcome over many years. Such data is lacking from developing countries.

      This multi-center study aims to systematically record the outcome of musculoskeletal
      function in people with hemophilia in developing countries for the first time and provide
      information that can help plan care for the 80% of all hemophiliacs in the world who live in
      these countries. Currently there is no well documented model of care at the range of factor
      replacement practiced in these countries nor is there any significant information on the
      long-term outcome of musculo-skeletal function among these patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      3.1 Musculoskeletal function in hemophilia - natural history

      Severe hemophilia is characterized by recurrent bleeding into large joints and muscles
      resulting in progressive damage and deformity by the time the patient reaches the end of the
      second decade ultimately leading to severe functional disability in many of the affected
      people. This fact has been well known for long. The orthopedic outcome of a person with
      severe hemophilia was perhaps not very different in different parts of the world till the
      1960s. However, in the last three decades, the ability of factor replacement therapy to
      completely modify the clinical outcome of severe hemophilia has been recognized. Factor
      replacement therapy itself has evolved much over this period and infusion of large
      quantities of factor concentrates has transformed the outlook of this condition. A person
      with hemophilia can now lead a nearly normal life without fear of frequent bleeding into
      joints.

      3.2 Factor replacement for preserving musculoskeletal functions - the current models

      As late as the early 1960s, factor replacement in large quantities was difficult because
      only fresh plasma could be used. With the discovery of cryoprecipitate in 1964, (1) larger
      quantities could be infused. Further purification and lyophilization made home-therapy
      possible. (2) It was soon obvious that early factor replacement could reduce joint damage
      significantly. Two schools of practice evolved: on-demand therapy where factor concentrates
      were infused at the earliest evidence of bleeding and prophylactic therapy aimed at
      maintaining factor level above 1% at all times. Both approaches required very large
      quantities of factor concentrates but could completely alter the expression of disease by
      preventing recurrent bleeding into joints. (3,4) What has facilitated this approach is the
      enhanced safety of plasma derived and recombinant factor concentrates. (5,6) Improved
      methods of donor selection and the introduction of viral inactivation steps in the
      manufacturing process have made these concentrates safer than ever before. (7)

      The most convincing data on the effectiveness of prophylactic factor replacement in
      hemophilia is from Sweden. As shown with carefully documented long-term data, perfect joint
      architecture can be preserved with large quantities of factor concentrates ranging in doses
      from 4,000-9,000 IU/kg annually. (3) More recently, similar data from the Netherlands has
      shown that with much lower doses ranging from 1,400-2,500 IU/kg annually, joint damage can
      be very significantly reduced. (13) Unfortunately, both these studies have not reported the
      disability status of their patients in relationship to the extent of joint damage. In other
      words, it is not clear from this data whether the person with a joint score showing mild
      damage is necessarily worse functionally that someone with joint cores showing moderate
      damage. However, there is often a very large difference among them in terms of the total
      quantity of factor replacement therapy. In fact, clinical experience suggests that there is
      often a poor correlation between joint scores and functional disability in the joint.
      Optimal regimens for factor replacement therefore still remain to be defined. Two large
      multi-center studies to evaluate regimens for prophylactic therapy are underway in Italy and
      Canada.

      3.3 Models for factor replacement in developing countries

      While these models of replacement therapy are very effective in preventing arthropathy, they
      have also made hemophilia one of the most expensive diseases to treat. (8) Therefore the
      benefits of such an approach have been limited to those people with hemophilia who live in
      developed countries. (9) For three quarters of people with hemophilia in the world who live
      in developing countries, treatment of this nature remains a distant dream. Most of them
      receive very little or no factor concentrates. Blood bank products continue to be used for
      factor replacement therapy. (10) As efforts are made to improve their care, it is necessary
      to develop more practical models for management of hemophilia in these countries.

      3.4 Aim of factor replacement therapy

      The predominant cause of morbidity in hemophilia is the damage resulting from repeated
      bleeding into joints. It has therefore been the aim of therapy to establish a standard where
      there is no evidence of damage to the joints, clinically and radiologically. (11) The
      effectiveness of this approach in preserving joint integrity has been so good that it has
      now become the standard for therapy in economically developed countries. Unfortunately, the
      annual cost of such therapy at $50-100,000/person has been so high that it has been
      difficult even for countries with developed economies to adopt it universally.

      It is certainly desirable for all people with hemophilia all over the world to have the same
      level of care. However, the reality is that it is simply not economically feasible. While
      the per capita GDP of developed economies are above $20,000, that of developing economies is
      in the range of $500-3,000. (12) Apart from this, attitude towards health care varies
      considerably with many countries spending less than $10 per person annually. In such
      situations, it is necessary to establish a different philosophy for factor replacement. The
      aim shifts from maintaining perfect joint integrity to reasonable joint function that will
      allow the person to remain functionally independent. Out of necessity and not out of choice,
      people with hemophilia in developing countries and their physicians have to accept this
      fact.

      The situation with factor replacement for joint bleeding in developing countries is
      variable. The limited data available suggest that the total quantity of factor concentrate
      used varies from about 2-30,000 IU/person annually corresponding to about 25-500 iu/kg/year.
      (14,15) Some of these centers that use factor concentrates in the intermediate range have
      reported preservation of reasonable joint function and functional independence. However,
      this is not backed by carefully documented data on orthopedic outcome. A systematic
      evaluation of orthopedic outcome with the different replacement protocols will help develop
      suitable models for treatment of hemophilia in these countries and will also assist health
      care planners in determining the cost of care. In recent years, considerable efforts are
      being made in many developing countries to get support from governments or insurance
      agencies for hemophilia care but the absence of adequate data on outcome with protocols that
      are practical in these situations makes it difficult to convince the authorities that even
      lower doses can preserve long-term functional independence.

      A unique aspect of this study will be the assessment of functional independence of people
      with hemophilia and its correlation with joint scores. Unfortunately assessment of
      functional independence measure in hemophilia has not been standardized. After much
      discussion at the WFH Congress at Seville and the subsequent meeting of the SSC of the ISTH
      with the prospective co-investigators and advisors, including Drs.Donna DiMichele, H.
      Marijke van den Berg, Bruce Evatt and Carol Kasper, it was decided to apply a generic
      instrument such as the WeeFIM&#174; till a more hemophilia specific instrument becomes available.
      This instrument is easy to administer and has been shown to have excellent consistency. (16)

      Baseline factor levels and quantum of factor replacement may not be the only determinants of
      musculo-skeletal outcome in hemophilia. Levels of other coagulation proteins, including
      presence of prothrombotic markers, can also alter clinical outcome. Polymorphisms of various
      modulators of the inflammatory response may play a role. Though it is not envisaged to study
      these parameters in this study, it has been planned to collect blood samples with informed
      consent for evaluating these some of these parameters in future, if possible.

      Hypothesis While it is likely that there will be good correlation between joint scores and
      functional independence at low joint scores, this correlation is unlikely to be linear or
      even significant, with increasing joint scores.

      This study aims to document the outcome of musculo-skeletal function in a large number of
      children with severe hemophilia receiving varying levels of factor replacement therapy over
      a long period of time with particular emphasis not only on joint scores but on the
      functional independence status of these patients.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2004</start_date>
  <completion_date>June 2009</completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Defined Population, Time Perspective: Longitudinal</study_design>
  <enrollment>250</enrollment>
  <condition>Hemophilia</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Severe hemophilia, defined as factor assay showing &lt;1% activity (assay to be done
             using standard reagents), between 5-15 years of age

          -  Be willing to come for evaluation at least once in 6-12 months for 5 years

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Detectable inhibitors by screening tests at recruitment
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>5 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>15 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Alok Srivastava, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Christian Medical College, Vellore, India</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Raul Perez Bianco</name>
      <address>
        <city>Buenos Aires</city>
        <state>Ciudad de Buenos Aires</state>
        <country>Argentina</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Margareth Castro Ozelo /</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chagas</city>
        <state>Cidade Univrsitaria Zeferino Vaz-Campinas-Sp</state>
        <zip>13 083 970</zip>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Elbio A.D' Amico / Jorge</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sao Paulo</city>
        <zip>01246 903</zip>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Magdy EI Ekiaby</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cairo</city>
        <country>Egypt</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Christian Medical College</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vellore</city>
        <state>Tamil Nadu</state>
        <zip>632004</zip>
        <country>India</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mohammad Reza Baghaipour</name>
      <address>
        <city>Teheran</city>
        <zip>14158 63675</zip>
        <country>Iran, Islamic Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Tien Sim Leng</name>
      <address>
        <city>Singapore</city>
        <zip>169608</zip>
        <country>Singapore</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Prof. Glynn Wessels</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tygerberg</city>
        <country>South Africa</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Prof. Ampaiwan Chuansumrit</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bangkok</city>
        <country>Thailand</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Norma De Bosch</name>
      <address>
        <city>Caracas</city>
        <country>Venezuela</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Argentina</country>
    <country>Brazil</country>
    <country>Egypt</country>
    <country>India</country>
    <country>Iran, Islamic Republic of</country>
    <country>Singapore</country>
    <country>South Africa</country>
    <country>Thailand</country>
    <country>Venezuela</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2005</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 29, 2006</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 9, 2006</firstreceived_date>
  <keyword>Severe Hemophilia</keyword>
  <keyword>Musculoskeletal Function</keyword>
  <keyword>Factor Replacement</keyword>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  
</clinical_study>