<clinical_study rank="131467">
  
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 05, 2016</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01047865</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>20053039</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01047865</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Type 1 Diabetes Recurrence in Pancreas Transplants</brief_title>
  <official_title>Recurrence of T1D in Pancreas Transplantation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Miami</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Juvenile Diabetes Research Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Miami</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The hypothesis is that humoral and cellular islet-specific responses are an early risk
      factor for recurrence of autoimmunity and hyperglycemia in simultaneous pancreas-kidney
      (SPK) recipients independent of alloimmunity. This study will test the hypothesis and will
      assess their individual and combined predictive value.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      To identify the factors associated with recurrence of diabetes in subjects who received a
      simultaneous pancreas-kidney (SPK) or pancreas transplant. The study will see if there are
      changes in the participant's blood that will help the investigator know whether diabetes has
      returned after the transplant.

      SPK patients will be retrospectively analyzed to determine frequency, levels and time course
      of autoantibody recurrence and predictive value of autoantibodies for recurrence of the
      disease.

      This study will prospectively follow our existing and our new pancreas transplant recipients
      to monitor autoantibody levels, monitor and phenotype autoreactive T cells in peripheral
      blood. This will happen monthly for 24 months.

      This study will assess the presence or absence of insulitis in the transplanted pancreas
      from biopsies performed in recipients with consistent recurrence of multiple autoantibodies.

      It will also monitor and phenotype autoreactive T cells from the pancreatic infiltrate
      obtained by pancreatic transplant biopsies.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2005</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Cohort</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Retrospective and prospective analysis of pancreas transplant recipients to determine frequency, and time course of autoantibody recurrence of disease. Prospective follow up to: monitor autoantibody levels, monitor and phenotype autoreactive T</measure>
    <time_frame>monthly</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Monitor autoantibody levels as well as phenotype autoreactive T cells in peripheral blood.</measure>
    <time_frame>monthly</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">295</enrollment>
  <condition>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 1</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>pancreas-kidney transplant</arm_group_label>
    <description>pancreas-kidney transplant recipients with type 1 diabetes.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      peripheral blood
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Type 1 diabetes who received a simultaneous pancreas-kidney (SPK) transplant
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient has been fully informed and has signed a dated IRB approval informed consent
             form and is willing to follow study procedures for the extent of the study (24
             months). Parent or legal guardian must provide written consent for patients &lt;18 years
             of age.

          -  Age 18-75 years.

          -  Recipient of simultaneous pancreas and kidney transplant

          -  Primary or secondary renal allograft: living or deceased

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient has previously received or is receiving an organ transplant other than a
             pancreas-kidney.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>George Burke, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Miami</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>George Burke, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>305-355-5111</phone>
    <email>gburke@med.miami.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Miami Miller School of Medicine Transplant Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Miami</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33136</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>George Burke, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vendrame F, Hopfner YY, Diamantopoulos S, Virdi SK, Allende G, Snowhite IV, Reijonen HK, Chen L, Ruiz P, Ciancio G, Hutton JC, Messinger S, Burke GW 3rd, Pugliese A. Risk Factors for Type 1 Diabetes Recurrence in Immunosuppressed Recipients of Simultaneous Pancreas-Kidney Transplants. Am J Transplant. 2016 Jan;16(1):235-45. doi: 10.1111/ajt.13426. Epub 2015 Aug 28.</citation>
    <PMID>26317167</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Burke GW 3rd, Vendrame F, Virdi SK, Ciancio G, Chen L, Ruiz P, Messinger S, Reijonen HK, Pugliese A. Lessons From Pancreas Transplantation in Type 1 Diabetes: Recurrence of Islet Autoimmunity. Curr Diab Rep. 2015 Dec;15(12):121. doi: 10.1007/s11892-015-0691-5. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26547222</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pugliese A, Vendrame F, Reijonen H, Atkinson MA, Campbell-Thompson M, Burke GW. New insight on human type 1 diabetes biology: nPOD and nPOD-transplantation. Curr Diab Rep. 2014 Oct;14(10):530. doi: 10.1007/s11892-014-0530-0. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25142715</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pugliese A, Yang M, Kusmarteva I, Heiple T, Vendrame F, Wasserfall C, Rowe P, Moraski JM, Ball S, Jebson L, Schatz DA, Gianani R, Burke GW, Nierras C, Staeva T, Kaddis JS, Campbell-Thompson M, Atkinson MA. The Juvenile Diabetes Research Foundation Network for Pancreatic Organ Donors with Diabetes (nPOD) Program: goals, operational model and emerging findings. Pediatr Diabetes. 2014 Feb;15(1):1-9. doi: 10.1111/pedi.12097. Epub 2013 Dec 10. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24325575</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ciancio G, Sageshima J, Chen L, Gaynor JJ, Hanson L, Tueros L, Montenora-Velarde E, Gomez C, Kupin W, Guerra G, Mattiazzi A, Fornoni A, Pugliese A, Roth D, Wolf M, Burke GW 3rd. Advantage of rapamycin over mycophenolate mofetil when used with tacrolimus for simultaneous pancreas kidney transplants: randomized, single-center trial at 10 years. Am J Transplant. 2012 Dec;12(12):3363-76. doi: 10.1111/j.1600-6143.2012.04235.x. Epub 2012 Sep 4.</citation>
    <PMID>22946986</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2015</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 9, 2015</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 12, 2010</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Miami</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>George W. Burke</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Surgery</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Type 1 Diabetes (T1D)</keyword>
  <keyword>Autoimmunity</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 1</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  
</clinical_study>